<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The accusation and impeachment of Iohn Lord Finch, Baron of Fordwich, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of England, by the House of Commons</title>
            <title>Proceedings. 1640</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837860</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837860</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 797:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The accusation and impeachment of Iohn Lord Finch, Baron of Fordwich, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of England, by the House of Commons</title>
                  <title>Proceedings. 1640</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 10, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Harper],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Finch of Fordwich, John Finch, --  Baron, 1584-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2207:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:2207:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <p>THE ACCVSATION AND IMPEACHMENT OF IOHN <hi>LORD</hi> FINCH, BARON OF FORDWICH, <hi>LORD</hi> KEEPER OF THE GREAT SEALE OF ENGLAND, <hi>BY THE</hi> Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Printed Anno Dom. 1640. <add>Jan. 14. 1641.</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2207:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2207:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
            <head>THE ACCVSATION AND IMPEACHMENT of <hi>John,</hi> LORD <hi>Finch,</hi> Baron of <hi>Fordwich,</hi> LORD KEEPER of the Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> by the Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mprimis,</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Finch</hi> Baron of Fordwich, Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, &amp;c. hath traiterouſly, and wickedly, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſubvert the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed government of the Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and in ſtead thereof to introduce an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary tyrannical government againſt Law, which hee hath declared by traiterous and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2207:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->wicked words, counſells, opinions, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, practices, and actions.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That in purſuance of thoſe his traiterous and wicked purpoſes, he did in the third and fourth year of his Majeſties reigne, or one of them, being then ſpeaker of the Commons houſe of Parliament, contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the houſe then aſſembled, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, denied and hindred the reading of ſome thinges which the ſaid houſe of Commons required to be read for the ſafety of King, and Kingdome, and preſervation of the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of this Realme; and did forbid all the members of the houſe to ſpeake, and ſaid that if any did offer to ſpeake, hee would riſe and goe away, and ſaid nothing ſhould bee then done in the houſe, and did offer to riſe and goe away, and did thereby and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in as much as in him lay, endeavour to ſubvert the ancient and indoubted rights and courſe of Parliaments.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That he being of his Majeſties Councell at the Juſtice ſeat held for the County of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex in the moneth of October, in the 10. year of his now Majeſties reigne, at Strafford
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2207:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->Langton in the ſame County, being then of his Majeſties Councell, in that ſervice did practiſe by unlawfull meanes, to enlarge the Foreſt of that County, many miles beyond the knowne bounds thereof, as they had beene enjoyed neare 300. yeares, contrary to the Law, and to the Charter of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Foreſt, and other Charters, and divers acts of Parliament, and for effecting the ſame, did unlawfully cauſe and procure undue returns to be made of Jurors, and great numbers of other perſons who were unſworn to be joyned to them of the Jury, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and awed the ſaid Jurors to give a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict for the King, and by unlawfull meanes did ſurpriſe the County that they might not make defence, and did uſe ſeverall menacing wicked ſpeeches, and actions, to the Jury, and others, for obtaining his unjuſt purpoſe aforeſaid, and after a verdict obtained for the King in the moneth of Aprill following (at which time the ſaid Juſtice ſeat was called by adjornment) the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Finch</hi> then Lord chiefe Juſtice of his Majeſties Court of Common Pleas, and was one of the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aſſiſtants for them, he continued by fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlawfull and unjuſt practices, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and confirme the ſaid verdict, and did then &amp; there being aſſiſtant to the Juſtice in eyre, adviſe the refuſall of the traverſe offered
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2207:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->by the County, and all their evidences, but onely what they ſhould verbally deliver, which was refuſed accordingly.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That he about the moneth of November, 1635. he being then Lord chief Juſtice of the Court of Common Pleas, and having taken an oath for the due adminiſtration of Juſtice to his Majeſties liege people, according to the Laws and Statutes of the Realm, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in opinion in <hi>haec verba,</hi> (when the good and ſafety, &amp;c.) and did ſubſcribe his name to that opinion, and by perſwaſions, threats, and falſe ſuggeſtions, did ſollicite, &amp; procure Sir <hi>Iohn Bramſton</hi> Knight, then and now Lord chiefe Juſtice of England, Sir <hi>Humfrey Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venport</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Lord chief Baron of his Majeſties Court of Exchequer, Sir <hi>Richard Hutton</hi> Knight, late one of the Juſtices of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Court of Common Pleas, Sir <hi>Iohn Denham</hi> Knight, late one of the Barons of his Majeſties Court of Exchequer, Sir <hi>William Iones</hi> Knight, late one of the Juſtices of the ſaid Court of Kings Bench, Sir <hi>George Crook</hi> then and now one of the Judges of the ſaid Court of Kings Bench, Sir <hi>Thomas Trevor</hi> Knight, then and now one of the Barons of the Exchequer, Sir <hi>George Vernor</hi> Knight, late
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2207:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->one of the Juſtices of the ſaid Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas: Sir <hi>Robert Barkley</hi> Knight, then and now one of the Juſtices of the ſaid Court of Kings Bench, Sir <hi>Francis Crawly</hi> Knight, then and now one of the Juſtices of the ſaid Court of Common Pleas, Sir <hi>Richard Weſton</hi> Knight, then and now one of the Barons of the ſaid Court of Exchequer, ſome or one of them to ſubſcribe with their names the ſaid opinion preſently, and enjoyned themſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſome or one of them ſecrecy upon their allegiance.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That he the  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap>  day of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  then being Lord chiefe Juſtice of the ſaid Court of Common Pleas, ſubſcribed an extrajudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall opinion in anſwer to queſtions in a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from his Majeſty, <hi>in haec verba, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that hee contrived the ſaid queſtions, and procured the ſaid letter from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; and whereas the ſaid Juſtice <hi>Hutton</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Crooke</hi> declared to him their opinions to the contrary; yet he required and preſſed them to ſubſcribe, upon his promiſe that hee would let his Majeſty know the truth of their opinions; notwithſtanding ſuch ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which nevertheleſſe hee did not make knowne to his Majeſty, but delivered the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2207:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->ſame to his Majeſty as the opinion of all the Judges.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That hee being Lord chiefe Juſtice of the ſaid Court of Common Pleas, delivered his opinion in the Chequer Chamber againſt Maſter <hi>Hampden</hi> in the caſe of Shipmony; that hee the ſaid Maſter <hi>Hampden</hi> upon the matter and ſubſtance of the caſe was charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with the money then in queſtion: a cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of which proceedings the Commons will deliver to your Lordſhips, and did ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite and threaten the ſaid Judges ſome or one of them to deliver their opinions in like manner againſt Maſter <hi>Hampden:</hi> and after the ſaid Baron <hi>Denham</hi> had delivered his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion for Maſter <hi>Hampden,</hi> the ſaid Lord <hi>Finch</hi> repaired purpoſely to the ſaid Baron <hi>Denhams</hi> Chamber in Serjants Inne in Fleet-ſtreet, and after the ſaid Maſter Baron <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had declared and expreſſed his opinion, urged him to retract the ſaid opinion, which he refuſing, was threatned by the ſaid Lord <hi>Finch,</hi> becauſe he refuſed.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. That he then being Lord chiefe Juſtice of the Court of Common Pleas, declared and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2207:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->publiſhed in the Exchequer Chamber, &amp; we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne circuit where hee went Judge, that the Kings right to Shipmoney as aforeſaid, was ſo inherent a right to the Crowne, as an Act of Parliament could not take it away; and with divers malicious ſpeeches enveighed againſt and threatned all ſuch as refuſed to pay Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money; all which opinions contained in the foure, five, and ſixth Articles, are againſt the law of the Realme, the ſubjects right of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and contrary to former reſolutions in Parliament, and to the petition of right: which ſaid reſolutions and petition of right, were well knowne to him and reſolved and enacted in Parliament when he was Speaker of the commons houſe of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. That he being Lord chiefe Juſtice of the Court of Common Pleas, did take the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall practiſe of that Court, to his private Chamber; and that he ſent warrants into all or many Shires of England to ſeverall men, as to <hi>Francis Giles</hi> of the County of Devon, <hi>Robert Benſon</hi> of the County of Yorke At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torneyes of that Court, and to divers others, to releaſe all perſons arreſted on any utlawry about 40. ſhillings fees whereas none by law ſo arreſted, can be bayled or releaſed without
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2207:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->ſuperſedeas under ſeale or reverſall.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. That he being Lord chiefe Juſtice of the Court of Common Pleas, upon a pretended ſuit begunne in Michaelmas Terme in the 11. yeare of his Majeſties Reigne, although there was no plaint or declaration againſt him, did notoriouſly and contrary to all law and juſtice, by threats, menaces and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, compell <hi>Thomas Laurence</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutor, to pay 19. pound 12. ſhillings, and likewiſe cauſed <hi>Richard Barnard,</hi> being one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overſeer of the laſt will of that Teſtatour, to bee arreſted for the payment of the ſaid money, contrary to the advice of the reſt of the Judges of that Court, and againſt the knowne and ordinary courſe of juſtice, and his ſaid Oath and knowledge, and denyed his Majeſties ſubjects the common and ordinary juſtice of this Realm, as to Maſter <hi>Limericke,</hi> and others, and for his private benefit enda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged and ruined the eſtates of very many of his Majeſties ſubjects, contrary to his oath and knowledge.</p>
            <p n="10">X. That hee being Lord Keeper of the great
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2207:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->Seale of England, and ſworne one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Privy Counſell, did by falſe and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſlanders labour to incenſe his Majeſty againſt Parliaments, and did frame and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe the publiſhing the declaration after the diſſolution of the laſt Parliament.</p>
            <p>All which Treaſons and miſdemeanours above mentioned, were done and committed by the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Finch</hi> Baron of Ford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England, and thereby he the ſaid Lord <hi>Finch</hi> hath trayterouſly and contrary to his allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance laboured to lay imputations &amp; ſcandals upon his Majeſties governement, and to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the hearts of his Majeſties liege people from his Majeſty, &amp; to ſet a diviſion between them, and to ruine and deſtroy his Majeſties Realme of England, for which they doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach him the ſaid Lord <hi>Finch,</hi> Baron of Fordwich, Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England, of high Treaſon againſt our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Lord the King, his Crowne and dignity, of the miſdemeanours above mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And the ſaid Commons by proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaving to themſelves the liberty of exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting at any time hereafter, any other accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation or impeachment againſt the ſaid Lord <hi>Finch,</hi> and alſo of replying to the anſwer: that the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Finch</hi> ſhall make un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid Articles or to any of them, and of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2207:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->offering proofe of the premiſes, or any of their impeachments or accuſations that ſhall be exhibited by them as the caſe ſhall accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the courſe of Parliaments require, doe pray that the ſaid <hi>Iohn,</hi> Lord <hi>Finch,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of Fordwich, Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England, may bee put to anſwer to all and every the premiſes, and ſuch procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, examinations, tryalls, and judgements, as may be upon every of them, had and uſed as is agreeable to Law and Juſtice.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2207:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
